Register of the Sergio d'Angelo papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Sergio d'Angelo papers
1957-2015
2015C14
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, and printed matter relating to the Russian writer Boris Pasternak and especially to the circumstances of the publication of Pasternak's novel Doctor Zhivago.
D'Angelo, Sergio, 1922-
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2014.
Biographical Note
Sergio d'Angelo is a former Italian journalist and acquaintance of Boris Pasternak. He worked as an editor and reporter for Radio Moscow from 1956-1957. On May 20, 1956, after meeting with Pasternak, d'Angelo was given the manuscript for Doctor Zhivago, which was later given to the Italian publisher Feltrinelli for publication.
In the late 1960s, d'Angelo was involved in legal battles regarding royalties from the novel. He also published a memoir about his role in the publication of Doctor Zhivago in 2006, entitled, Il Caso Pasternak or The Pasternak Case: Memoirs of a Witness.
Scope and Content of Collection
Writings, correspondence, and printed matter relating to the Russian writer Boris Pasternak and especially to the circumstances of the publication of Pasternak's novel Doctor Zhivago.
Arrangement Statement
Material is not arranged into series, but has been kept in the original order of the creator. Most of the original file names have been maintained and are indicated with quotation marks.
Pasternak, Boris Leonidovich,1890-1960.; Dissenters--Soviet Union.; Russian literature.
- "Corrispondenza con Doubleday e Bompiani su A Captive of Time,", 1977-1978 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains correspondence with the American publisher Doubleday and Italian publisher Bompiani regarding A Captive in Time by Olga Ivinskaia (also spelled Ivinskaya).
- "Royalties D. Z. [ Doctor Zhivago],", 1966 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- "Lettere mia a Olga dell'aprile 1959," (Box-folder 1: 3)
  Contains drafts of letters to Olga Ivinskaia, Pasternak's confidant and partial heir to the rights of Doctor Zhivago.
- "Lettere di Olga Ivinskaia a me e Giulietta,", 1959 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  Contains letters from Ivinskaia to d'Angelo and his wife, Giulietta.
- "Lettere di Pasternak,", 1959 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  Contains mainly copies of correspondence between d'Angelo and Boris Pasternak.
- "Importante!,", 1959-1969 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  Contains letters and statements that d'Angelo refers to in his work, The Pasternak Case: Memoirs of a Witness. Includes five subfolders titled, "Questione possibili aiuti a Olga e figlia," "Minuta mia lettera a Krusciov," "Minute mie lettere a Pasternak," and "Lettere Cambiaghi, Scuderi, Bianciardi, [e] Carlo Ripa di Meana."
- "Corrispondenza con l'FSB [Federal'naia sluzhba bezopasnosti] (per archivio KGB [Komitet gosudarstvennoy bezopasnosti]),", 2001, 2007-2008 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- "Curiosita!,", 1958-1961, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  Contains correspondence, news clippings, and a booklet with handwritten notes.
- "Cartoline Pino Santo e lettere Micello a Giulietta (ritrovate ultimamente) e una lettera della Zamoiska,", 1958-1960 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  Contains postcards and other correspondence.
- "Mia corrispondenza con W. Middleton (Floyd/Kuznetsov),", 1959, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 10)
- Yale correspondence, 2006 January 12 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  A letter from the editorial director at Yale University Press acknowledging the receipt of d'Angelo's manuscript, The Pasternak Affair. Also includes a photocopy of the letter.
- "Osservazioni al Testo di Valerio Riva," typescript, undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
  Contains typewritten notes on an unidentified text.
- Transcription of an email to Paolo Mancosu, 2014 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  Contains a partial transcription of an email from d'Angelo to Paolo Mancosu, a professor of philosophy at UC Berkeley and author of Inside the Zhivago Storm: The Editorial Adventures of Pasternak’s Masterpiece, describing materials originally given to Mancosu and later added to this collection.
- "Foto dell'Autobiografia di Pasternak,", 1957 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  Contains a photocopy of Pasternak's autobiography given to d'Angelo by the author in 1957. The text is in Russian with some handwritten Italian translations.
- " Il Caso Pasternak appena riveduto e aggiornato da me,", 2014, 2015 (Box-folder 1: 15-16)
  Contains two typescript revisions of The Pasternak Affair in English.
- "Ritagli di articoli,", 1961, 1967, 2007-2013 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  Includes newspaper clippings from Italian and American publications about the Zhivago affair. Also includes a printout of an online Russian article.
- "Alcune recensioni italiane del mio libro,", 2006 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  Contains Italian reviews of d'Angelo's Il Caso Pasternak.
- "Mi articolo su OstEuropa,", 1968 July (Box-folder 1: 19)
  Contains a copy of the publication in which d'Angelo's article, "Der Roman des Romans," was printed.
- "Lettera di Irina [Emelianova] a E. B. [Evgenii Borisovich] Pasternak,", 2004-2005, 2014 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  Contains a letter from Irina Emelianova (also spelled Emelyanova), the daughter of Olga Ivinskaia, to Evgenii Pasternak, son of Boris Pasternak. Also includes a letter from Emelianova to film director Eldar A. Ryazanov and a printout of an email chain between d'Angelo and Emelianova regarding the two letters.
- "Response to the Objections of Evgeny Pasternak" and "Interview on Inge Schoental,", 2007, 2011 (Box-folder 1: 21)
- Vita, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  Contains volume 5, numbers 108 (May 11) and 109 (May 18). Includes d'Angelo's article "Olga è innocente" that spans both issues.